hey it's professor Dave, let's talk about
redox chemistry.
an oxidation-reduction reaction or a redox reaction is
one in which electron transfer occurs. take for
example this single replacement reaction.
watch what happens if we write out the
net ionic equation. the sulfates cancel
and we see that the only chemistry that
has occurred is that two electrons are
transferred from iron to copper. iron has
lost electrons so it has been oxidized.
copper has gained electrons so it has
been reduced. it may seem confusing to
associate a reduction with a gain of
electrons so instead associate reduction
with a reducing of charge. copper 2+
had its charge reduced to zero when it
gained two electrons. more electrons
means a more negative or lower charge.
the substance that is oxidized is the
reducing agent because it's the thing
that caused the reduction in the other
substance. likewise the substance that is
reduced is the oxidizing agent because
it caused the oxidation in the other
substance. we will use oxidation numbers
to keep track of electron flow. these are
like hypothetical charge values for each
atom in a molecule but they are not
actual electrical charges. here are some
rules for a signing oxidation numbers.
for an element the oxidation number is
always zero. if it's a monatomic ion the
oxidation number is the same as the
charge on the ion. oxygen is almost
always -2 except for in peroxides
so we can usually assume -2. for
a neutral molecule oxidation numbers
must add up to zero so if the oxygens in
carbon dioxide are each -2 the carbon
must be +4. for polyatomic ions the
oxidation numbers must add up to the
charge on the ion and hydrogen is almost
almost
always +1. using these numbers for
oxygen and hydrogen we can usually
assign all the other numbers accordingly.
let's take a look at a reaction, on the
left we have elements so those have
oxidation numbers of zero. on the right
we know oxygen will be -2 and
there's three of them so we need iron to
be + 3 for everything to add to zero. this means
the iron was oxidized since its
oxidation number increased. oxygen was
the oxidizing agent. oxygen was also
reduced since its oxidation number
decreased, that makes iron the reducing
agent. let's check comprehension
thanks for watching guys subscribe to my
channel for more tutorials and as always
feel free to email me